Yes.
And welcome to week three, open source, circular Fashion
with Zoe Romano.
I give you the floor so that you can
Okay. Thank
Us. Everything about
Yes. Thank you.
And welcome to this new class.
Happy to, to see all these new faces for the,
this edition of Fabric Academy.
Now I share my screen.
Yes. This one?
Mm-hmm. Can you see Yes,
Yes. If you had
videos. Did you have videos in
Your presentation? Yes, but
the sound is not, is not necessary, so, okay,
Perfect.
Uh, let me see if I can, okay. Hello.
So I'm glad to be here for the ninth year,
and since the beginning of this, uh, adventure venture,
I felt myself, uh, very comfortable with, um,
the approach of fabric academy
because I'm a kind of, um, weird, uh,
let's say maker because my background is in philosophy.
But, uh, I had a master in media science and technology.
And, but I, I work mainly at the beginning.
My professional, uh, life started
with the working in strategic communication.
And, uh, I mean, it was more for the digital, uh,
um, digital becoming of companies
moving from the leaflet to the website.
And then I also, while I was working, I was doing that job,
I, I worked at as a media activist.
And I will tell you a bit about this approach.
Uh, after that, I worked for Arduino team for four years
and to manage the communication
and also a bit of community and wearable technology.
And then in 2014, I co-founded one
of the first maker spaces here in Milam
that was focused especially on design and fashion.
So, uh, since 2019, uh, I'm a freelancer,
so I left the managing of the makerspace.
And I'm actually in, I'm more able to
focus on projects.
I'm more able to focus on specific vertical project,
especially funded by, uh, European Commission.
And, uh, and usually they are, uh,
touching topics like, uh, social impact, um,
being driven by, uh, open source
and digital technologies in, uh, especially right now,
because when I say this, the definition where I work,
I say, yes, but what do you do?
Basically, for example, right now I'm working on this, uh,
woodshed project that is based on the alpine space,
on the mountains, on the Northern Italy
and other four countries in Europe.
And we are looking at how to solve the issue
of coarse wool.
So we, in the alpine spaces, we have a lot of sheep,
and we sheep we have sheep
because we, uh, they are good animals
to manage the landscape,
but also we eat the meat of the, of the sheep
and make cheese outta their milk.
And the specific of this, uh, ship is
that their wool is not really soft as the merino wool
that is the most used wool in, in the fashion system,
but is a wool that is thicker
and is, uh, coarser is stronger, is more richy.
And so we are finding way to, to work on it and use it.
Otherwise, it's been treated as a, as, um,
waste instead of being a resource.
We have a tradition in Italy,
but also in the other aine spaces where this school was
considered a, a special precious material
because it has a lot of, um, features that,
that makes them, makes it a very, um, precious
regarding being able not to get into fire,
being sustainable, being, uh, soft
and can be used to keep the heat, for example,
inside the houses, so many, many features.
So what we are trying to see if, how in which way we can use
and make other products out of this tool.
For example, here, I collaborated
and made a little research case study on, uh, how
to tuft, you know, the tufting technology when you shoot
with a gun, the gun that I like, the guns that shoot wool.
And, um, we attached together
with local studio in Madrid, we attached this, um,
tufting gun to a robot,
and we started to test all the wool
that I brought from Italy
of different type of, of breed of ship.
And so we are understanding if we can work on a concept
of microfactory in the alpine space that can,
uh, manufacture the wool
and also create products at a higher value.
So this idea, this approach is a kind
of systemic design approach in which you think a problem,
an issue, a material that is precious
and in which way you can have this material
to be used locally and not moving it around in the country,
but being there, being able to create a more,
a small supply chain
and use digital fabrication in order to engage young people
in making up startups
or small companies that can create these type of,
um, products.
And, uh, um, in,
in within this cons concept, I also teach
in inside the Theus Academy, I, I make a course
that is called Cradle to Cradle Fashion Making.
And it's about how to apply making,
so digital fabrication technology within the idea
of fashion manufacturing with a sustainability, uh,
a sustainability, um, approach.
So being able to have products in which,
you know, what happens to the products at the end of life.
Um, recently I took part, uh, actually last year I took part
to this, uh, conference that is called,
that was titled Commons in Design,
and actually was trying
to understanding which way we can apply design, uh,
within the framework of the commons.
And I, in, in this book, there is a, a paper, uh,
like a chapter that I wrote that is called Low Tech,
is the New High Tech.
So in which way, somehow we are trying
to merge the traditional manufacturing system with
the, uh, contemporary manufacturing system to find a balance
between the two and find solution that can be conceived
as digital, uh, distributed manufacturing.
And during this lesson, I will try to, um,
dive you into, into this concept, understanding
what does it mean digital, uh, distributor manufacturing,
in which way the commons
and the concept of openness is really important
for this new framework of production.
Um, one of the, another paper that I wrote,
this is older, but I think is still valuable
and interesting, is the, um, idea that
the new designers are, um, need to
conceive and design products that are easily repairable.
And the easy of repair is for us,
a design a DL in the sense that
repairing shouldn't be something
that someone else think about when a product is broken,
but it's something that can increase the
lifespan of products.
So first responsibility of designer is to conceive
products that have this, um, easy easiness
of, uh, uh, repairing in.
Uh, but how did I arrive here?
In which way I, I, I,
let's say, discovered the idea of openness.
Um, first of all, I talk about,
I talk about in which way the idea of openness, um,
uh, helped us, uh, conceive a new way of,
uh, thinking about fashion, especially Milan.
Milan is a city, I mean, that is full of fashion and design.
There are design weeks
and fashion weeks, um, more than once time a, a, a year.
And most of my friends, um, at the beginning
of the century was really, uh,
working for this.
I mean, when you are 20 years old, when you want to work
with, um, uh, you're studying
and maybe you need to have some kind of job, you go
and work for like fashion catwalk or things like that.
And there is a lot, and you realize
that there is a lot of exploiting.
So the exploiting is not just outside
of in the countries where we manufacture the fashion,
but is also in the window of fashion, in the branding,
in the, all the communication, uh,
in all the communication, um, situation.
Sorry, my phone. I thought it, it was okay, my phone.
Um, and,
and so we discussed a lot about,
in which way, as activists,
we were working a lot in thinking about the precariousness
of life, the precariousness of having always to deal
with the, um,
with the temporary jobs.
And in this, uh, in this framework, we decided to
create a fake fashion designer
that entered the official calendar of the fashion week
to somehow disrupt
and denounce the exploiting of creative workers
during the fashion week.
Um, we did it
because we had the skills to create high quality
communication and high quality, um, designs.
And, uh, we actually created a big event
in 2005.
So this year we celebrate 20 years of activity.
Uh, and during that event, we actually
were reflecting, and this is a book,
talking, talking about us.
If you want to know more about the,
the, let's say the reflection of some, uh, academics
around our work.
Uh, we created a big event in which, uh, we
presented the 10 allegorical garments to reveal
the, the exploitation in the Milan creative industries.
But we did it first creating a fake fashion designer
that applied to the official calendar.
And then when it was accepted,
because actually the official calendar
of the fashion week didn't ask to see any garment,
they just wanted immaterial stuff.
They wanted the, the brand, the trademark.
They wanted the, the book, a digital book
with all the designs that we wanted.
Of course, we didn't, we didn't give them this one,
but we gave them fake.
We did a fake book, uh, look book.
And that was well done, uh, and, um, but with fake garments,
and we were accepted officially,
and we created a catwalk in which instead of showing
the right garments that we presented in the Look book,
we created this allegorical garments
in which you see, for example, the garments to hide the,
the, uh, to hide the pregnancy,
because where they know that you're pregnant, they fire you,
or the, the job of like having double,
when you have a double shift during the day, you need
to change during the day or the garments when you need to.
They ask for a woman and they,
or they ask for a male to be, to take the job.
So we made this 10 garments in order to
present in which way our exploitation was happening in,
uh, in, in Milan.
But this was, uh, full of people because we created a fake.
Uh, also, um,
we pretended that the activist of
the Milan scene were going against this designer
because she pretended
and she offered the activist some money to have the catwalk
inside an occupied space, a squat.
And so this thing, uh, made the journalist very curious
to understand why
and why there was this fight between the activists
and the fashion designer, but both of them were us.
So, I mean, it, it's a long story,
but you, you understand the, the, the main story.
And the, the day after it was, we were all in,
in all the newspapers, and they talked about us
and workers on the catwalk.
Um, I mean, there was a lot of, a lot of talking
and gossiping, and most of the, um,
most of the newspapers talked about us,
but the Chamber of Fashion sent, um, a message
to all the fashion magazines to,
and told them not to talk about us
because they had, they felt ashamed
that they accepted us in the,
in the official calendar.
And, and so I guess that a couple of years
after they changed the way to apply to the fashion week,
but since then, we created, um, uh,
an association, an open, an association that kept doing
and reflecting upon the garments that reflected upon,
um, how to make fashion in a different way,
in which way the patterns could be open source
and in which way people could learn how to make things.
We also experimented with technology here, for example, one
of the, uh, workshop that we do is, uh,
making laser cut stencil.
And then we, we have these events of upcycling,
so you can come with your old garments
and you can, uh, create your own, uh, upcycling as upcycled,
um, garment with our, uh, designs.
This is, you use a roll with the silk print, uh, ink,
and then you just did do it.
And it's like happening. It's very nice.
Recently we opened up, uh,
actually this year to celebrate the 20th years we had,
we have a gallery now in Milan,
and we use it as an empty, like, it's like a shop,
and we use it to make exhibitions
and to make, to invite, uh, designers
that are, uh, like more ecological and more ethical,
and they don't have, and they have usually small production,
and they don't have the money to rent a shop in Milan
because it's really expensive.
The rents for, also for exhibitions are skyrocketing.
So the idea to was to make, uh,
a community space in which to present, um, new
projects that were focused on al fashion
and a new approach to, to fashion.
And it's open. You can join the community and come
and exhibit in, in, in the center of Milan.
And, uh, this idea actually in this 10 years, 20 years
of activity, the, the, the path that we took was
to move from the hack, the hacking practice.
The hacking is about when you have a product,
when you have an object that you are not happy about it,
you hack it, so you break it or you, you, you open it
and you, it's a kind of reaction of something
that you are not happy with,
and you make a customization maybe, or an
or open up something to fix it.
So this is the first act of openness.
You physically open the object, understand how it works,
and you make some changes.
Then we have the second phase
and is about the making That started when digital
fabrication became more widespread,
and actually is the attitude to discover, to learn,
activate processes for the creation of, we say useless
and useful devices.
Because a lot
of learning comes when you also create useless
objects, because you learn in the process, you learn
by your errors, and this is,
you can do it when you can share an infrastructure,
an infrastructure together.
And it's a part of the process of prototyping new ideas,
prototyping something that usually the for-profit
companies are not making.
And we think that the final step of this growth
to think about openness is about open design.
That is the, the discipline in which as a designer,
you really create objects that are maker friendly,
that are, they can be digital
and physical devices embedded potential.
They have the potential in their being, in their design
to be modified, to be fixed, to be improved by others.
So is a systemic way to approach openness.
And we think for us, this is the design that we like.
Uh, after, uh, CICA narrow, I, I started
to make my first open, uh, uh, sorry, my first, uh,
um, EU funded project that it was open wear.
And this open wear project was, uh, a way to
bring to the designers the concept
that came from Anaro project.
And so we created a new open source brand.
There's, that was called Open Wear.
We made a collaborative collection
and we create a license to use the, the, the brand.
And also we shared all the patterns.
It was around 2009, 2009 and 10.
But what was the issue since in those years
that I realized only afterwards that most
of the education in the fashion schools
was about making patterns by hand with pencil and paper,
and very few designers, fashion designer knew how to draw
with digital tools, with digital softwares.
And so we couldn't reach the critical mass
to have this community to grow.
And that's why I'm really happy
that this academy is happening
because there is a lot of lack.
There is a lot of lack of knowledge
and skills in the fashion.
Um, schools around digital fabrication now is a bit,
uh, it's a bit better.
Uh, and one of the, also, the
collection that we did was open source accessories
and wearables that were this pattern that were digitalized
that could be used directly on the laser card.
There was the, they were the templates in which you could
start from learning how to work with
digital technology, and especially laser cut.
This, for example, was a workshop that we did during
Milan design week in 2000,
and I think it was, uh, 10 or 11.
And we brought the laser cut in the, the design week,
and we did with felt this shoes that were just flat,
but you could, um, fold it and sew it,
and it was also useful to prototype wearable technology.
I made this workshop,
and that's how I, I met Massimo Bandi from Arduino.
I brought my knowledge about this digital pattern.
And then Arduino
and Massimo Banzi was working with students.
It was a summer school, uh, was working with student in
developing and prototyping, um, open source devices
with, uh, Lily Duino and another, and other boards.
Um, and I was helping the student to make the wearable part.
Um, in later, I also talked to, uh,
at the Parsons School in New York.
I was invited to talk about all these, all these, uh,
experiences that we made.
There is still some paper
and a journal around this if you are interested.
So all started with this idea
of openness definition, actually.
Um, I was working
and being active in, um, in, at the end
of like the century.
So 98 to 99, I was, uh,
in hacker spaces here in Milan.
And in those years, it was the term blogosphere,
I don't know, it's not used so much now,
but in, in those years was very used.
It was the first idea of, uh,
it was actually a neologism, a new word
to express the real of the internet, self-published blogs
where people share the text, images
and links in order to pre freely accessible
and read by others.
So this idea of sharing online.
So the idea
of openness has since then become an umbrella concept
referring to increased accessibility of knowledge,
technology and other resources.
But also it came to signify, uh, a different approach
to the production of knowledge itself.
So pushing us to reflect on the transparency of action
of any organization, recognizing that
to foster the diversity of contributions, it was necessary
to reach a high permeability of structures, how
to take decision in which way decision are taken within a,
uh, institution.
So the political implication of this new environment started
to be discussed within the hacker counterculture,
and it happened since the mid eighties, right,
where the ideas of free
and open source software drove most
of the material infrastructures
that turned the internet into a worldwide medium.
So the first concept of openness,
and it was about free software.
And so, uh, actually,
Richard Stahlman within the Free Software Foundation
invented and popularized the concept of copy left
and the, um, uh, that is a legal mechanism
to protect the modification.
And there is distribution rights for free software.
So he start, he studied at Harvard
and then became a programmer at MIT
joining the Hacker debate,
especially clarifying the meaning of the world.
Free. Thus, free software is a matter
of liberty and not price.
It is not just a, it is not
that you just download free software,
but the, the, the, the liberty within the concept of free
is more similar to the idea of free speech,
not as free beer.
So we sometimes called it Libre software.
Taking the word Libre from French and uh, uh,
and also free is a kind of freedom to show
that we do not mean the software is gratis is for free.
So the ambiguity of the term free anyhow generated
a lot of misunderstandings
and many coders chose to use an alternative
that is open source
because that became a more widespread, widespread, um,
and less political option,
especially in the commercial field,
even if it shares many practical features
with free software.
It focuses more on the technical issues
of software development
and also avoiding themes around user freedom and and ethics.
So this, this concept than gave the opportunity
to create new licenses to share
a piece of code that you can share online.
So he, he, this is a table that you can find online.
So free is a matter of liberty, not price.
Open doesn't mean access to the source code free refers
to price, while freedom of the use is restricted by creator.
So there are different type of licenses
that you can explore.
And the most open one is, is the public domain software
that is belongs to the public as a whole,
and it doesn't have any copyright law.
But also we have a new type of licenses
that are referring to a different type of content on data.
So if we take a, if we don't talk about
software anymore, but we want to deal with content
and it's pictures, any content related to creativity
and covered by copyright or data, but also design.
So we have more restrictive and
or less re restrictive licensees
that you can choose when you want to share your,
um, idea.
Your design in fashion
actually is a bit different
because the pattern of fashion are not covered by copyright,
uh, because it is, uh,
serving purely a functional and purpose.
While the laws
is different in different country, it changes a lot.
So if you want to go into that, you can follow this link
and explore if you're very interested.
There are some kind of best practices.
And in, uh,
ideally, so the idea
of intellectual properties in the fashion industry actually
is not used, not just because it is utilitarian, but also
because registering something is takes too
slow, is too slow for fashion,
because you have a lot of production
that happens every six months.
And, uh, so it doesn't keep up with the shortlived trends
of the seasonal collection.
And so what brand use usually is the trademark.
And so when you put a trademark on something, it becomes,
uh, covered by a type of intellectual property
that is helpful not to let the,
the consumer be confused about who is producing that object.
Um, the, in 2011, this book
that is called Open Design now, was published in,
um, in, uh, hall the Land in the Netherlands,
and also is still a nice resource if you want
to explore in which way designer were thinking
to create new business model related to releasing
blueprints of objects,
or that could be fashion, that could be, uh, furniture
or anything under some kind of license,
given the possibility
and the freedom to others to digitally, um, modify
and locally produce these, um, type of objects.
So, um, from the idea of openness, uh,
we moved also in this idea of the commons
because this idea of openness we,
that we talked about until now is really related to digital,
to digital objects, something that you can share online.
But when you move to digital fabrication, when you move
to something that you make physically, uh,
something has to change, something has to, uh, be,
um, reflected upon.
So actually, digital fabrication became very widespread,
especially for the, uh, the creation
of two main tools.
One is the Arno controllers, the Arduino controllers
that were very easy to use
and accessible in price were used inside
many other machine, like for example, 3D printers.
And there were also on the base of this
and the creation of this new objects, a lot
of new communities came up.
So the idea of makerspace
and FabLab, we had make magazine and maker fairs happening,
and then, uh, fab, uh, uh,
fab academy and, and, and,
and, uh, fab conferences happening,
but all started, especially with the
beginning and the, uh, becoming accessible
of 3D printing technology.
So the wrap wrap project was, I would say it's the mother
of all the 3D printers, rep wrap,
meaning replicating rapid prototyping
because it was an initiative that,
uh, could print 80%
of the pieces that you could use to make a new machine.
So you actually had the parent, um, 3D printer
and the child 3D printer,
and it was running on Arduino, the family tree from this,
you can find it on Wikipedia or,
or some other wiki that you can find.
From this first example of documentation
of this machine released online, a lot
of all the machines started to replicate.
And so you can see the timeline from 2006
to 2011.
Of course, we had other 10 years,
but I just to say that these were the first 3D printer
that managed to be created,
and not all of them were just documentation on,
on internet, but they became businesses that would sell,
uh, kits that you could buy online and,
and with instruction to create your own 3D printer.
So, uh, in the same years,
there is this other thinker that is called yo, um, UI Bank.
Uh, he wrote the Wealth of Network,
and this professor, he created this term common based
peer production to describe wherever and
whenever people freely associate
and create digital commons together,
which then become shared resources that are maintained
by a community or a group of stakeholders
through their own rules and norms.
The peer aspect refers to the level of openness,
or rather the capacity of people
to join these open networks of value creation without asking
for formal permission.
So this idea of sharing all the knowledge,
no one ask you who are you?
Are you a designer? Are you an engineer? No, anyone.
You could be in your home.
You could be a student, you can download all the
documentation and you can replicate your own 3D printer.
You have any issue, you write on the forum,
you join a community, no one,
you don't need to ask permission.
So, and in, in this, in this idea
of not asking for permission, it means also that you can
also create, um, you can create some kind of economy.
And in fact, that the peer-to-peer foundation,
that is another, uh, nonprofit organization
and global network that is dedicated to the, this idea
of common oriented, uh, manufacturing production
or solutions.
They wrote, we believe that a new type
of economy will be evolving whereby open design are combined
with distributed physical production, the capability
by individuals, designers to produce design,
have them produced by 3D printers in a physical format
and with access to local
or distributor labor for producing them.
So somehow a new economy came out
of this, a new economy
that is based on open design principle.
So there there's been, uh, a reflection
of coming up with a open design definition.
So open design is a design artifact
whose documentation is publicly available, uh,
but also, uh, is not just that.
It is not just that you publish the file, it's not enough,
but it, it should be made or it should be created.
You should create it using readily available components
and materials, standard processes, open infrastructures
and restrict content
and open source digital tool to maximize the ability
of individuals to make and use hardware.
So right now, one of the platform that is really pushing
to make this happen and create an event around this
and is the distributed design project in
where they're publishing
and understanding in which way there is, uh,
there should be an ecosystem to make this, um,
um, new world of objects happen.
Because let's remember these things,
this type, this new ecosystem don't happen if you work
alone, don't happen if you just stay in your home
and you just do your things.
It's really important to network with peers, to network
with other people like you
and to share infrastructure, to share knowledge.
And, and in 2005, um,
after all these, let's say years of thinking about openness,
we have this idea
and the, the explosion in the good sense of, uh,
makerspace and FabLab in a global network.
And the idea of digital fabrication
move from being just, you have an input design, uh,
a file, you share the file,
and then you put it in a 3D printer,
and you have your object in some type
of interactive fabrication in which the designer is not the
person that creates the objects,
but the designer, it is the person
that creates an interface, a framework
of a parametric design that can be modified by the user
to reach the, the ability
of the object in term of small changes.
And after that, you can click a button
and order the object through that type
of fabricated object that is customized and personalized.
Uh, and the, this interactive fabrication somehow
is the one that has been, uh, has been
celebrating a lot of change
and a lot of in interesting projects
around it just to frame this, uh,
envision this approach in a, in a,
in a longer period of time.
If we think of manufacturing
and production from the pre, uh, pre-industrial
revolution in which we had local workshop in which
you had craft
and craft lab creating objects,
we move into the centralized
on the first industrial revolution,
the second industrial revolution,
the third industrial revolution in which
all the production is still very centralized.
What it changes is the capacity of,
uh, not wasting too much time in setting up
the, the, the production.
And, uh, you move you
and you have a low cost of the products, and you have,
but you have high number
and you can really control
the production also depending on
what the consumer is consuming in at the end
of the supply chain, but is still linear
and is also, uh, not
very fitted on the final user.
What we like about the new situation
and what we see as an opportunity is the first industrial
revolution because you can have local factory that,
that are very high, uh, high um, technology.
They, they can contain high technology like robots,
but the setup cost is not super high.
And you can create many type of products
that can be mask customized and,
and is especially, um, focused
and managed through open design and data led design.
Um, of course, when we make objects,
it means that we need to use materials
and which type of materials should we, shall we use,
is not something that we cannot think about.
And one of the objectives
of the fab city globalist initiative is also
to understand in which way our cities could become
places in which we can produce
almost everything that we, that we consume locally,
of course, is not something
that we can create in like 10 years,
but it's something that it will take some years.
But the idea is that we can
share globally
and produce locally taking the resources of materials
that we can find locally
and find ways to reuse what could be considered waste.
And here we go back, of course, you don't,
you shouldn't think just of the city,
but for example, the project that I told you about,
about the wool, this is, this is something that I'm trying
to apply in a rural area in which we have,
there is a resource that is a material,
and we could use digital fabrication to create locally
product that can be consumed by local people,
because now it's really important
to think about the supply chain.
We cannot make something that is sustainable if we don't
reflect upon the supply chain and this supply chain.
Of course, we know that circularity is a kind of,
also, we have a lot of greenwashing in that we know
that most of the plastic cannot be recyclable.
Uh, I'm not going into that,
but it is really important to focus on the material
that you use and what are the marketplace
of this new type of products.
The new products that are based on openness
and micro factories.
It's what we call the long tail model
that can help you understand how to position our products.
So if we consider the niche products, the one
that are luxury, high-end with, um,
with many, uh, also like craftsmen making it,
that if they are made by high,
uh, mainstream brand are highly products,
but made in niche products,
we can position ourself in this sort of kind of popular
in which there are unique products that are created
and customizable locally, in which there are many type
of products that can be created on demand
on specific territories.
Um, so some example, uh,
one of, I mean, this project is, is not, uh,
is is not working anymore, but it's still a nice example.
I mean, it is 10 years. Uh, I liked their approach.
And so I give you, I give you this an, an example,
but it's also understand is under, is nice
to understand why it does it didn't work.
Uh, so, uh, they shared, um,
laser cut, um, designs in
that could be produced in, um, in local maker spaces.
So they create also network of maker spaces
that could produce these, uh, garments.
Um, another project that is interesting that you can look
through is the open footwear.
Uh, I, I'm recently,
I'm recently using barefoot shoes,
and so I'm really curious to try this new approach to
barefoot also here it's a shoe
that you can make in a makerspace.
Um, then we have Atak that is, uh,
a project in which they created an area
of the website that is called Shareware
that you can explore and they made,
and they're sharing some nice pattern
that you can download.
You can give like, uh, some contribution,
but also you can download them for free.
They suggest a price, but you can download it for free
and it's nice to, uh, as a starting point
to explore open source pattern.
There is also, this is a 3D camo is a hoodie in which
you buy a construction kit
and you can, um, compose
and assemble your hoodie at home
and is losing, is using interlocking
as you will do in this exercise of this week.
But what I like about attack C price model is that
they have an increasing price in, in the sense that you,
if you pre-order, you pay, uh,
66% of the price.
If it's in production, it then the, it goes on.
And this stock, if it's in stock.
So that means if you already order,
if they already produce the object,
you're gonna pay the a hundred percent of price because,
and this is a nice idea to really think also
of the production, uh, ways, the,
the ways in which on demand production can happen
on short, uh,
or small batches of, um, production can be, can be used
that are interesting, uh,
because we come from a world in which
the price is fixed.
But somehow I think
that right now we are in a moment in which it's important
to really, um, let's say benefit people
that are bringing some support to the project.
And bringing some support means, uh,
having faith on something and pre-ordering
and being transparent also with the price,
showing people in which way we are, uh, in which way we are,
um, composing the price
of the object that we sell.
Um, going back to the materials,
it's, uh, thanks also to the new rules by European Union.
Of course here we, I'm talking about European Union
because that's where I live.
And, and there are new, a lot of new norms
regarding sustainability.
And now brands cannot throw away or burn leftovers.
So a lot
of new shops online are happening in which you can find
leftovers of textiles.
This non project is, um,
a big conglomerate of fashion, uh, um,
oh, let's say
platform in which they sell the leftovers of their textile.
So it's really high quality good,
and it cost, uh, a fraction compared
to buying it directly.
And this is the opportunity that new designers,
contemporary designers can have to reach
high quality textile without having
to spend too much.
You don't have it only with textile,
but you can have it also with leather.
So this, uh, French, uh, platform allows you to
buy leftovers of leather mainly.
They also have some fabrics,
but they are recovering all the leftovers from
companies that are working with leather.
And so you can buy some pieces to
make your own, uh, limited edition objects.
Like, uh, this is one example I've been working, uh,
in the past years of, uh, on ideas
of micro factories, the idea
of micro factories about moving from a digital design
of a customized product,
customizable product in which a client enter the shop
and you make thanks to technology, the the object
directly in the store.
I wanted to show you a video.
I mean, there is a sound, but I mean,
So here the idea was having a family of bags
that could be made.
So you imagine a client that enters the shop
chooses the color of the leather.
So we have like a hanger with many different colors
of leather leftovers.
Of course you choose one, we laser cut the part
that is the, let's say the the raise, and then we attach it,
and then you choose the bladder cord
and you have the, um,
weaving of the bag directly.
So we, in one hour you can create your basket,
your bus basket, leather back.
So this idea came
because this idea
of having a service for companies that wanted to
have their own shop to make directly
an object, an accessory in the store,
and we could sell this service to clients.
Um, so what is the,
the, the idea
and the alternative model that we want to provide
and we want to, uh, experiment with?
And we want to figure out in which
way this can be possible if in the city,
if in the countryside is to move
from the traditional way to conceiving
a fashion accessory of a fashion or a fashion product.
And, uh, we want to do this moving from
stop conceiving the idea of the product,
but, um, conceiving a
platform instead of a product, a family of, uh,
of products with the same, more
or less the same design, a strong idea that can, uh, open up
to different type of customization.
Instead of thinking of seasonal collection, you can think
of an evolving catalog based on open codes
and the openness.
The idea of openness is not about, I share my design
so people can really make it for free.
I mean, you would love that people make it for free
because usually when you share it, only 1%
of people are doing it.
All the others, if they like, they buy it.
And also this idea of
mass production, the only way
to stop the pollution of the is, um,
the fashion industry is to limit
mass production and move
to an on demand or small batches production.
So we don't have leftovers, we don't have to burn,
we don't have to like throw away
and we don't have to recycle
because all these are not good for the planet.
So distribution in stores, this idea, we know
that when we move, when the cost
that we pay to produce an object, for example,
you produce a bag
and from the idea to the production, it cost
life cost is a hundred euros in the store,
the cost will be 300 or 400.
Because having something in the shop costs per k,
because the shops have high costs, pay a lot of taxes,
they have someone to stay in the store all day.
So it is not something that, because they're greedy,
but really you need a lot of, you need a lot of, um,
expenses to have a store.
So one solution to have lower prices is to sell
directly online or locally creating
situation in which maybe you have a place
where you can store your prototypes, your templates,
and then people go online
and order a version, a customized version.
So, and this, you can do it in collaboration with others.
That's why I always say you need to network.
You need to contribute and collaborate with others.
And instead of having venture capital to fund
a lot of, uh, in a lot
of situations we have crowdfunding
or pre-selling that works.
So you launch a product like the example that I gave you,
and you have and you have, uh,
clients that are ordering it because you know you're ready.
You created a community of people that know,
know about your work because you also share the design.
So more than having like, like a company
that just think about the, the object
and the distribution is a kind of community of users
and early users that support your work
and are ready to give a contribution when
and when you produce and when you manufacture.
And in this way, I think there are some ingredients
that you can take from to create your own ideas.
And thank you very much.
If you have any question, I will stop sharing.
Probably there are some questions
or
Hello.
Wow. Hearts a lot of logos.
Mm. Shall I check the page of the question? Okay.
Is anyone, uh, not, uh, Alex,
Can I ask a question?
Yes. I'm curious.
I see a renaissance in young people
wanting to learn how to sew.
Would any of these, um, uh, these, uh, ways of thinking
of manufacturing include bringing people in to make some
of the parts themselves so that people could be trained in?
Yes, handcraft,
Yes, of course there is somehow
you can really design your products in which
maybe you already sell a kit of pieces.
That with also the tools to finish some parts.
But the important thing is to have, uh, tutorials online,
maybe a video on how to do it,
or maybe you can use the laser cut to really say in which,
where to put the needle, you know,
because sometimes it, there is a,
you feel disappointed when you create something
and then when you see it say, oh, my hand, were not so good.
And it is bad. So you as a designer, you have to make it
as easy as possible in order to the final customer
to make something that is good, that is the objective
of the designer, the, the purpose of the designer to
simplify the process in order to do it.
So when, uh, there is, uh, a project
that is called another shoe that is, uh,
like also there 10 years ago in which we did it in,
we did a workshop of this other shoe that you could make
with laser cut.
And they were coming to my makerspace
and they were testing with users
how they were assembling the shoes.
So before launching the product, they were doing some kind
of focus group and see how much the, how, how is difficult
to me because maybe as a designer you think is easy,
but then you try it and make a, a group
and you test it and say, oh my god, no.
And you can see how the people interpret the tutorial
guidelines and see what is the outcome.
And so it helps you as a designer to draft and,
and create a tutorial that is really going
to the right direction to fulfill also the, the people
that are not really good with their hands.
Thank you.
Any other question? Don't be shy.
Uh, thanks for the lecture. It was very inspiring.
I wanted to ask, some of the projects that you mentioned
that are, uh, based in the European Union are mostly
or in part government, uh, funded.
I'm curious to know if you have an opinion on, uh,
what can we do on in countries
or you know, places
where we don't have this kind of support.
Like what is the landscape looking like, looking like
and what are others doing so we can, uh, make this work?
Okay, so yes, um, for sure.
I mean, not all the things
that I showed you are government funded.
So, so some of them, um, for example,
the, when I set up my makerspace in Milan,
there was no funds.
So I had to go and talk with people, make events
and fight people that would like to invest in a maker space.
And so we put together the resources.
So the idea is to see what do you have in your country
that could support you?
Sometimes they can give you some funds for technology.
They give you some funds for like, uh, I don't know, spaces.
There are many things that you need to start a project.
So when you lack on something, you can have on other things.
But before launching into a venture that, uh,
that needs money is good to test it in,
in m in a small environment, for example, this idea
of the shoe, for example, you before setting up
and buying a laser cut, you can go
and have a membership in a maker space and test and, and
and prototype the, the objects.
And then when you have a very strong concept,
you can start, uh, like the venture
in a makerspace and only when the business goes you can say,
okay, I can buy my own laser cut because it works.
So there is always step by step,
and it depends a lot on understanding in
what they give you in your country.
Sometimes they give you acceleration programs,
sometimes they give you, I dunno, many things.
There are always money is out there.
So somehow money, money, not the means they give you money,
but resources in the sense spaces, knowledge sharing,
machine sharing, um, these type of things.
Usually there are so never work alone.
The you should, you should find some Ali.
Thank you. Thank you, thank you Zoe.
Uh, uh, we can um, now move on, uh,
because we will have to continue
with the more technical part of the presentation.
Um, but um, yeah, many.
Okay, thank you. Yes, thank you.
So I will be next week in, uh, reviewing the work.
Yes. Okay. See you next Tuesday.
Okay. Thank you very much.
And if you have any questions,
just write me an email or whatever.
Okay. Have a good week. Bye-bye.
Thank you. Bye. Yeah, bye. So,
Okay, I think you can see my screen.
Uh, let me know if you cannot hear me.
My connection is not that great today.
So I think it's time to move on with the more practical part
of this open source circular fashion lecture
that will focus on an integration
with the digital fabrication technologies specifically.
Once again, the laser cut.
So today in this presentation we'll talk about, um,
patterns, materials, fabrics, and of course digital design.
Specifically, we will focus, um, seamless patterns.
So we'll exploring, um, clothing systems
that can be designed to be modular, adaptable, uh,
reconfigurable and of course designed to be disassembled.
We we'll have a look at aspirations at many applications at
the state of the art, and of course at project
that you may be already based on our open catalog
that is open source secret fashion.com.
That also many projects
that have been done in this past nine years
of fabric academy, but also from people that contributed
that were outside of the community.
And this is actually the location where
after this week your creation will be uploaded.
When we, um, look at the patterns, I also want
to bring back a couple of things.
And so I highlighted in the presentation, so it's 2025,
and we all know that it's time
to rethink the way we consume, we produce
and we dispose materials, uh, goods
and specifically fashion.
So we are all in different locations of the world
and we're still all surrounded by trash, but landfills
and fashion scrubs, uh, this older the, um, model
of taking, using and discarding materials
that really work anymore.
So trying to embrace here, um, this concept
of circular economy, this is what we,
we should really take into account.
So trying to keep the material in use for as long
as possible and making clothes that can easily, um,
repaired, remained, um, closing the loop so
that nothing really goes to waste
and only this patterns.
With this kind of clothing
and systems in mind, I would like to show you a couple
of principles and approaches
that we can implement in our workflow,
and they're all independent interdependent from one another.
So, um, we, the use of laser cut this week, this is
what will make possible to create modular patterns without,
uh, any waste or at least
to minimize the waste as much as possible.
Uh, we, we'll, uh, not use any stitches, any seams.
So we'll produce seamless garments
that can be imaged without, um, a sewing machine
that can be reconfigurable through,
um, through interlocking.
So like a puzzle like Lego brick that made of soft materials
so that every piece in the system can be adopted,
can be also upgraded, repaired, uh, replaced, uh,
without the need of replacing the old garment
or just buying a new one.
Uh, when you talk also about digital fabrication,
we talk about open design for local production.
So a design that can be shared all over the world
and where different people can contribute.
A design can, can be remixed in, uh,
human location overseas,
and that can be customized also on demand so
that you don't need any physical stock.
So all these approaches together really contribute
to make fashion more adaptable, accessible,
and more sustainable.
This is a sneak peek at the workflow of
what you will be doing this week.
It's one of the earliest example
that we have in Fabric Academy by an aluminum set.
I'm Jessica Stanley, and, uh, what I want to say here is
that this important also to look at the module,
but also to look beyond it at the old system
where every piece, um, somehow a meaning can integrate,
can fit in, can interlock, and can evolve.
Uh, this then this week you'll be coming up your own
module with your idea.
We will digitalize it through a two vector file, uh, design
or, uh, 3D modeling software.
We'll laser cut, um, like you can see here in the picture,
ensuring there is no waste, no scraps left,
and we'll assemble in many possible ways.
So let's have a look now at some projects
that have been developed in fabric that also, uh,
were out there before
because the concept
of seamless clothing is actually something, uh,
that was there more than 10 years ago.
This is one of my favorite collection.
It was made in 2013
and made its first appearance at the Tokyo Design Week.
Uh, it's made by Croatian designers
and very much focused on the module of a square.
So it's only one module, uh, laser cut
and to at different scales, able to interlock
with similar modules to create, uh, this 3D stunning
and intricate configuration.
And with the same kids, it's interesting
how we can build not just a punch, but actually accessories
and garment at the same time.
Uh, so I talked briefly about that.
So this is the Prosecutor collective initiative, a project
of more than 10 years ago in the Netherlands.
That was the first time was introduced in the concept of,
um, open design, modular design
for fashion in a fab lab in MakeSpace.
So we, uh, we could go to produce and laser cut
or CNCA chair for the first time.
Uh, the, the maker, um, community there could have access
to templates they were ready to cut for making your own, uh,
fabric, a different range of materials, uh,
moving forward with different kinds of modules.
I always appreciate the work.
I mean, in Japan by zuki,
it's a single module cloned over and over the same size.
And it is also interesting here that we can, we,
the same module, you're able to recreate, um,
different kinds of items of garments
and this, for example, living cocoon.
So something that actually goes out of the silhouette
of the body and expand in multiple directions.
Uh, speaking about modules
and kit, this is a nice example by in Soho, uh,
very polygonal
and very geometrical, um, different, um,
triangles at different sizes, still able
to interlock with one another.
And we can see here an example
of custom customization also at another level,
we had different materials, different colors,
different textures and different ways to distribute the, um,
the modules in different locations of the body.
Um, we're not of course limited to use, um, straight lines,
polygons, or regular shapes.
So this is the same, uh, designing,
but of course a completely different approach.
Also here, the laser cut is used to produce kind
of a decoration perforation in some modules that is started
of being, uh, based on, uh, geometric lines and polygons.
Uh, you can see here more introduction of, uh,
naturalistic elements or more organic lines.
Um, we're still speaking about modules and constructions.
Uh, uh, favorite of mine is the work, uh, collection
of metabolism of 2015.
So we're still 10 years ago in Japan.
Uh, Ola Ang I made a great collection based on the module
of a square, and I also invite
to have a look at this extensive research, my hand.
Then you can find it on the website where you can see
how the sketches are turned into this module
that allows itself to be fully closed and become 3D.
And the same module allows you to create this kind
of reconfigurable, um, jacket, but also skirt
and a bag, all according
and inspired by this Japanese movement of the sixties,
about the configurable architecture were
initial integration.
But of course, you're not limited
to apply this constant technique, uh, fashion.
We can also talk about furniture, for example.
Keep in mind this picture on the right,
because I went back to it, uh, in a couple of slides.
Uh, so it's interesting
how here you can also develop this kind of flat patterns
that can be allow you to cover, uh, furniture in the house
like VAs, uh, objects, couches,
chairs, and of course carpet.
So imagine a carpet that can grow in any size according
to the size of the room that also welcomes, uh,
different quality elements that can become 3D at any point.
Or another good example is, for example, bags,
basket collections.
I really appreciate the work of Oscar mascara
and this is using a sort of leather scraps.
So it's also nice how through open design, digital design
and fabrication, we can also make use
and rethink, um, traditional.
So next, this example, um, it was getting inspired
by weaving and we can adjust design for creating these kind
of modules that don't need other supportive material
to interlock and create kind
of cell closing baskets and containers.
And on the same concept of packaging,
I always appreciate the work of km.
That was also the win or one of the red of the word in 2019.
This is a very clever idea, I believe.
Um, this kind of reusable packaging that is made
to fit any item basically.
So from the bottle to the book, um, all the way to grocery,
it is one single module that interlocks in an easy way.
And you can see here on top of the slide, like kind
of a detail, uh, to fit any item,
um, to the resolution.
Um, the laser cut, let's say,
and the precision that we can work with,
but also the vector file.
Were of course able to also work at the very tiny, uh,
scale, like in the case of jewelry.
This were also, uh, different leftovers
of different materials.
Um, is approached also in the Netherland
around five years ago that launched this kind
of collection featuring accessories like hats, bracelet,
earrings, and necklace that you can customize
with any material color
and let them grow in different locations.
Uh, we're moving now to see what the Community
and Fabric academy, uh, made in these past years, not just
during the secular fashion week,
but actually during workshops.
Uh, event boot come.
And I always like to begin, uh, with this project.
I really appreciate fact textiles
and, um, university Veritas in Costa Rica.
It's a growing point show there is, uh, quite intricate,
but is actually made of a single module that is repeated
and cloned over and over a module of composed
of two circles, like a chain that are joined together,
which, uh, where one as an opening
and one as a full shape that goes inside like a chain.
Um, we can talk about, um, traditions.
Arabic patterns are also a common source
of inspiration in public academy.
I appreciate, uh, the two versions.
Uh, they're based on the same module of a triangle here
and made in completely different locations
by two different students.
So in the first case, we have a address that was created
with this kind of, uh, decoration on the back.
And the second option is, uh, basically material
and, uh, mod that we cut to produce these long sleeves.
Uh, we have a lot of example of bags in fabric academy.
So, um, with the same 2D models, we are actually able
to convert them in something 3D to something
that fully closes.
Uh, we're talking here about, uh, male
and female connections.
We have two example of bugs, one made in mold, uh,
three years ago and one of last year, uh, in FBLA Barcelona.
You can see how, for example,
the same model can actually be used to provide
s additional material like the handle.
Or in the second case you can add the rope towards, um,
including multiple materials in the design.
Um, this is the slide I was referring earlier when showing
the application on furniture So you can look at
here, the modules.
One is the front, the one is the back.
Sometimes the back can also be the front.
So we have the same modules.
It's a combination of female part
with male parts in a single module
that is closed over and over.
Um, this modules become 3D
by bringing tensions in different location of the module.
For example, here when you can see this, these lots
where material is stacked on top of each other.
And in some cases where you have this kind of perforation
with the laser cutter, you can also, um, ing
because you can always, uh,
add additional material like rope, um, uh, threads.
So you can bring extra tension
and you can let this configuration to be pulled
to create something that can actually close completely.
And this is the case of a bag.
So it's a very similar construction.
Uh, you know how this sphere is made, so it's kind
of a different, uh, pentagons together.
And this is the base, the pinkish base of this new print bag
that is laser cut.
And I think that this project is very clever
because in order to hide the interlocking joints here, uh,
m mine maona was uh, able to also integrate these more, um,
istic objects inspired by the ville flower
and stuck on top of the connection, um, this kind of basis
towards, so make the bag, um, more personalized,
more catchy, more towards the team.
Uh, layering is also one of the technique, uh,
used when we talk about seamless models, seamless garments.
We have many options of kind of poncho kind
of colors in fabric academy, uh, using the male
and female connections.
And in Montreal was creating this kind
of feather feather poncho using one module
and different stripes, like if it was,
if they were interwoven, uh, within each other.
So there are rows of alternated modules
that are closed in the back.
And in the second case here, uh,
demon Jordan was creating this color with a similar idea
of creating a feder poncho
with a different construction technique.
So you can see here in detail, there are two, three,
and four modules that are actually able to join together
through another module that you can see hidden here.
So it's kind of across
that brings them together onto different rows and columns.
Ami um, ami is a Japanese word that stands for, uh, cut
and fold and is a technique can also be implemented in your
seamless clothing, seamless models.
I appreciate the work of Beana here.
Clear inspired by architecture by Za Hadid.
And you can see here detail of the module on the sketch.
So it's solely one module that allows the connection
to be formed in multiple locations.
That has kind of a b that is laser cut
and allows at the same time, one part the module
to sub close on itself
and bring a connection with the others.
So it's only one module repeated over and over again.
And we talk about kigami
to talk about collapsible structures.
So you might have seen this, uh,
during the first day of fabric.
This is also another approach that we can use
to produce zero waste bottles.
Imagine if you have one sheet of material
that can actually become something, uh, like your outfit
that is ready to wear.
I dunno if you can see from far away here at the bottom
there is, uh, the digital design, how a series
of lines like the living ingested your plug on wood in order
to be banned that are concentric,
where the only waste in this drawing is actually a circle in
the middle where you're supposed to, to put your neck.
Uh, still speaking about kigami
and going to see some example
that actually make use of upcycling.
Uh, I want to mention the work of giant, uh, haja farm.
So inspired by waves, by oceans,
the scrub up was actually, um, the final result
of a big three meters square curtain, uh, in velvet
that she had in the hand.
Um, so this curtain was laser cut into different stripes
and through a series of cuts
and fold, like, uh, car C explains, she was able
to combine them together without the use
of any additional materials.
And what is interesting to look at here is actually
that even though the models were laser cut flat,
what she actually uses is the back.
So this side along the thickness of each of the sides here.
Um, so I was speaking early, so we're all surrounded
by a lot of trash
that we can convert into treasure sometimes, uh,
in our home, in the lab, the make spaces.
And this was the project of here in Jordan.
So she had a lot of different little pieces
and scraps from different material available.
And, um, it, it was great what she did.
So she, uh, mapped them,
she traced all the dimension of each of them.
She laser cut them,
and she created this beautiful hut, uh, colorful hu
Um, s about cycling, an interesting project.
Um, this case, we are in Florence, uh, with Philippe
in the academy at that time.
And he had access to a lot of industry waste,
like fashion waste from leather of, uh, Ganon Fendi.
And he created this beautiful kind
of animal snake resembling the, the python, uh,
distilling this kind of, uh, shapes in a perfect way
that they applied later on, um, to the boot.
And on the way to this final project together
with 3D printing, Uh,
still about upcycling, uh,
one more project in the Middle East, uh,
where there are a lot of disposable bags like single use
bags and plastic.
I appreciate here the work of Naim, that he converted this,
um, this trash, this plastic bag into an activity for kids,
um, with guidelines.
And we provided them in order
to create their own animals, their own mats.
Uh, so there are these kind of five modules, uh,
that interlock within each other.
And at the same time, they were able to create this kind of,
um, colorful lamps for their bedrooms.
If you master any of the, um, genetic
or matic, um, design software,
you can also simulate in advance what your final assembly,
final configuration can look like.
And this example of the work, what has done also, uh,
getting inspired by Arabic patterns.
So this was a wall partition
and appreciate here the use of op, for example,
to create together with the laser cutter, this kind of, um,
perforations in the moles.
So you could allow the light to come in at any point,
uh, hoping to see, um, joints.
Uh, joints can also be a sort of decorations.
The example here is research of in
and, um, it's a great example of a t-shirt.
So we are not talking about models,
we're talking about replication to bigger pieces we can see.
Now here, um, on the left there, the four pieces
that are actually composed this t-shirt that is clear by,
by weaving technique.
And what I appreciate
that you can also check on a documentation
is research behind.
So lot of tests is disability with leather.
So you really have to make, uh, the connection work
for the kind of material that you have at your hand.
And then I have, uh, the product I really want to showcase,
which is the work of sterman.
So you can have a logo, you can have a picture,
you can have, um, an inspiration that you can convert,
uh, into a module.
And this, for example, where the moon phases
that we're serving at the same time as a decoration,
but actually a technical module of female
and male parts that interlock with the other two grade,
this top living top, but also cape.
And I also like to look at the back here
and to see that this kind of illustration comes back.
Um, there's a project of a steer now believe I will
also still connecting.
It's connected here. Um,
so a student had made use of personal grids
and this project was part of a final project was this, um,
seamless bag inspired by the shape,
the texture of the beetle.
So also like the way, um, that he was, uh, going back
through bio mcr, trying to resemble through pixel art
as well, uh, different locations of the body, of the color
of the animal, and trying to match this, uh, with pieces
that could hide the interlocking parts on the back.
And together with this, you also made, um, jackets
and let's say, um, that are kind of kids that are puzzles.
There are actually 735 pieces
that can help you make 21 different pieces.
And you can see, uh, a little bit the work here.
There are three different models, uh, that have female parts
with different cuts
and male parts that allow you, um, uh,
to be stuck together in different locations.
And I have a video, uh, later on that also we showcase this,
uh, uh, clever application that somehow was resembles
in 3D mdo one animal skin.
I also appreciate the work
of Vivian in New Montreal a couple of years ago.
So using a grid to create a modular smoking.
So how we can reshape, how we can manipulate the fabric
together with the digital design and the leather cut.
So imagine if instead of buying 10 different outfits
and different dress, so you can just create your own, uh,
variation every time.
And I think that this is a very clever idea to share
what you have a base
with a different perforations in this case holds squares.
And you have a kit of different shapes that can be inserted
to bring distinction
or to let the fabric fold
in different designs in different way.
Had a student also work, uh, a similar concept,
but more towards, um,
what we can call mod uh, modular heritage.
Mm-hmm. Um, this is very,
it is a great project about Palestinian embroidery
and how we can redesign these motives
that have been taught only traditionally
for such a long time and made them at the same time, uh,
more accessible to the younger community.
So it is a project that, uh, in a similar way
of the previous, uh, project as a lot
of preparation is black vest.
And you have a kit of different small modules
that can be insert in grid to create, um,
many kinds of motives.
So I, I'd say this, um, this project also has a sort of a,
of a value in terms of education.
So the kids were at the same time learning
about their lost heritage.
And there is another one that became a final project
is the work of Allic.
Um, is actually, um, talks about the story of Allah.
Allah was, and this project talks about the genocide
that happened at the SEC Cassian people.
They were the Muslim museum part of Russia many years ago.
And I appreciate here how Allah have been struggling
to find documentation of motives of patents.
Um, they used to be present on their costumes,
as you can see in the picture.
And, um, she digitalized during our experience
of fabric academy, these basic motives,
and they were reconnecting her with all roots.
And there are now part of this costume designs, uh,
of these sleeves that were used for performances.
Um, same software, same designs,
but opposite fabrication technologies.
We have been seeing some example about subtractive
fabrication technology like Lisa Cutter.
And we can see now an example
of application to, to keep printing.
So additive manufacturing.
And this is the work of Bridget Co.
Um, their brand of variable sims, who was one
of the first students that we had in public academy.
So it's interesting here how you can use the same file
that we can produce this week
and, uh, able
to produce in the computational wick at the same time,
your own TPU fabric.
So something that also can be elastic
and behave like a textile.
And at the same time a modular, uh, kit
to create your own collection.
Uh, TPU of course also comes in sheets, so it's something
that you can get at your hand
and you can laser cut if you're interested in this kind of,
uh, configuration is a material that is quite stiff
so it stays in place.
It's less bendable than fabric
and it comes also in different thicknesses.
So this is the work called RAF colada.
And we had a nice activity this year in plague, uh,
at the fabric conference.
And you can see also,
I can maybe recognize now there is a kigami signed
or there is a connection, um, that is made
through this arrow that allows the models to interlock
in this, uh, um, in this part of the module,
Of course, um, you can close the loop, uh,
you can apply the same techniques, use the same vector file
and uh, on your own material for example.
So we're gonna approach some believe it's week
seven by your materials.
So you can also think of applying, uh,
what you're gonna produce this week, uh,
to your own materials,
whether they are a gag based or gelatin base.
So at the end, uh, of their life,
if they com they compose it, they, um, can be discarded.
If there are damaged, you can always recoup them into a new
sheet and fabricate new system, new outfits, new models.
And of course the same thing is also true for, um,
bacteria cellose in the this case.
For example, we have a, an example here of a Kobocha bank
and uh, last panelist is a project
of Eduard de Loreto Bio Q tools.
So it's also an application, um, bio materials, uh,
from Ros using the same module
to produce different kinds of outputs.
So a combination of biomaterials, bio fabrication
and digital publication.
Um, there was a concept that I showed earlier in the slides.
So the distillation, the selection basically means
it's a process of fitting, uh, shapes together in a combine,
in a board a material, and ensuring there is no gaps
or overlap at any point.
Um, it's also what we call the dramatic division
of a plane in tile work, Zas.
And the two picture that you see here at the bottom are
actually two perfect examples of the distillation.
When there is no gaps, there's no space in between
and there is no overlapping at all in the same way,
for example, of course triangles always are perfect example
of the distillations, uh, regular polygons,
likes and so on.
The ations is everywhere, is around us, is inside us.
There are many examples from the natural world,
natural phenomenon in the animals of the, in the skin
of the animals, in the pattern of the animals,
in the plants, in the leaves at,
of course at the microscopical level and also on the minors.
If we put our skin on the lens of the microscope,
we might find kind a desolated oid.
And this is also what happens in the small parts of the body
or at the, the wing looking at the wings of a dragon fly.
So I also use this, uh, slide as a reminder, uh, to think
of the diversity of disciplines
that we work in fabric academy
and how we can also, um, take from biology, from the math,
uh, from design and also from computation emerge all
these aspects together.
Of course, uh, we can also talk about art
where tessellations have been present since Asher was
creating his mar masterpieces.
And there is a couple of tricks, uh, to produce this kind
of tessellation using your own drawings of patterns.
So Asher was using a series of, um, mathematical rules
that can be also translated into symmetries.
And uh, we can definitely look at the tomorrow
during the tutorial in the same way.
Um, in the Arab world, in the Middle East, in Spain
or wherever you are in the world, maybe you have traces of
Islamic patterns, Arabic patterns,
and these are all definitely great
example of the installations.
Something that you can definitely recreate with any
of the 3D modeling software, um, blender,
fusion, RH or software.
Let's have a look now at the patterns.
So what happens behind, how can they really connect?
So, um, I like to start simple
and start identify, define two, um,
two different patterns as you see here in the picture.
And start from the female.
So we can look at those, uh, two parts that get together
and they block because in the end you should able to pull
and they should be put, they shouldn't be assembled.
So, uh, let's have a look at the female.
Uh, we can take a, a circle as a reference here
and see a female object, like something
that has cutting lines, something
that will open once laser cut
or slots, something with an opening, uh, for some material
to, um, be put in.
And I like to look at the mail here, like, um, apart
with four different, um,
like t-bones, like arrows.
So this is the material that will be folded
like in this picture will be inserted
because the textile is something flexible.
And so you're allowed to do that and then will be released.
And this part, because it is definitely bigger than this lot
that you have, this two together will be blocked.
Um, if you're ready, reach this level,
you can definitely start iterating your module
and create something that is actually a
combination of the two together.
So we have two slots for a female module
and two parts for the male.
So instead of producing a laser cutting two full sheets
of female parts and two sheets
or male parts, you can just definitely go
for the third option.
So you can use one module, uh,
to recreate the same scenario here.
And if you master any of the 2D graphic software,
you can actually preview in advance how
the modules can get together, what kind of assembly,
what kind of configuration you can create.
So this is the same two, uh, circle that you saw here
that used in the previous slide, the same connection,
the male and the female that's also here.
So, um, what changes is just the outside of the shape
that sometimes changes their system, their mood,
their whole idea or their whole application.
The way they connect together is basically the same.
This is an example, um, gons
and of course you're not limited to use only two.
We see an example of stacking modules together
or welcoming different shapes, not regular, more organic.
So you can also add on top of each other,
but also, um, in between them.
On the back you can create your own system,
you can cut out things, you can create fruition,
you can engrave things with the laser cut.
And this is also another sneak peek to
what you will be asked to do this week.
So, um, while uploading your file in open source secure
fashion together with pictures
and showcasing your beautiful government,
you can actually add a couple of guidelines to somehow
prescribe how to battery interlock the pieces together
to recreate, uh, your project.
And you can find this once again on the documentation
of Jessica Stanley.
And what I want to say here is that the more slots,
so the marketing lines that you add
and the more possibilities you are prescribing
for the models to get together.
And if this cuts, if the cutting line, if these lots are,
uh, in the center of the model,
most likely you're gonna end up with something
that looks like an animals.
So you're gonna have a lot of pieces
layered on top of each other.
And this is the video I was talking about earlier.
So this is the project of ra.
It's kind of a jacket that is made
of three different modules.
And this is, uh, I think the resolution, yeah,
it's locked this to give an idea
how we can assemble and the many
different possibilities that we have.
So we have this, uh, male part that gets folded, insert
of the way inside and then gets released to block the piece.
And in this way you can definitely create connections
but also, uh, 3D sort of manipulations
because you're bringing tensions in different
parts of the module.
So what is the workflow of the week?
We'll definitely start with inspiration.
So having an idea, translating them, um, through sketches,
paper C and then moving on to digitalizing through
to the vector design or 3D modeling software.
You're gonna test the connection
before, um, printing out on the laser
or the way all your models we're gonna nest.
So, so as everybody comes to the sation, we're gonna try
to reduce as much as possible, all the waste,
reduce also the machine time at the same time.
And then we finally laser cut it and assemble it.
And one of the, one of my favorite project,
I think is this one by Susan that really, uh, showcases
what the profit workflow looks like.
Uh, we start with the idea in this case was an inspiration
ticket, I believe, in a temple.
And we started recreating them with very simple material.
If you cannot do it on the paper, you will never be, um,
be able to do it on fabric as paper really believe, um,
behave like textile.
So it's interesting how, um, to see also
at the different steps how, um, through just the circle
and a square she was able to get back to the idea.
And this is what I believe is a perfect installation.
So there is a module that is made of male part
and a female part that allows the connection to happen
between the modules
and everything fits perfectly in a square.
And this is how it looks like when it's laser cutted sort
of rows and column and it's been clothed all over the board.
And last thing to mention is
that I think it's very interesting how this, uh, kind
of carpet looks like in the end
because you can also see in the negative part appearing this
kind of cross that was actually used
as inspiration for the assignment.
And I also want to say
that the software is definitely a matter of workflow.
So I I actually use the for them together.
Sometimes you have many options this week, um,
you have been using for now 3D modeling software
and of course vector design to nest your file.
So, um, you can definitely create your own workflow
or give it a try, um, to paramedic modeling, for example.
So either, uh, fusion 360 or uh, glass software for Rhino
or, um, one of the add-ons for blender
and start doing that from scratch.
The advantage of starting with the 3D modeling software is
that once you have the file there, you can work for example,
at the same time for the 3D printer later on,
or, uh, you can do the other way around
and import later on the PNG, the the SVG and the PDF
and then proceeding to extrude them.
Uh, couple of things were the laser cutter, uh, so
we're gonna work with vector fi.
So, uh, very important to set the, uh, for example,
the color space of the vector
design software that you'll be using.
Either Inscape illustrator
or any other open source software that handles, um,
colors vectors.
So setting them to LGB, creating of course closet loops
for the laser card to be able to cut out
and set the stroke line to 0.1 millimeter
or hairline when possible.
This is what a perfect nesting looks like.
This is a project of Stephanie Johnson in
Amsterdam couple of years ago.
So you can see, um, the laser cutting bed
with all the modules together and the outcome.
So no gaps, no relapsing at all.
And be sure also to remove the double lines.
Uh, we are speaking about this earlier, so
of course there are many ways, there are many applications
that actually, uh, nowadays take care of the nesting.
For us. This is more useful, um, for the CNC machine,
for example, where we have also different sizes.
I usually do the nesting, uh, by myself
or there is a catheter, but of course you're welcome to use
and try out many software
that are available on the internet.
SVG Nest, uh, works very good for SSVG
and vector files as well as deepness to io.
And finally, um, laser cutting file.
Um, laser cutting will not take forever.
What will take forever is actually the sample part.
So, um, once you have your kit,
you can explore different configuration, different ways,
different applications also.
So this is a very nice example of loose gers.
This is our kit made of different, um, ware shapes,
all the different sizes they were able to interlock, um,
in different, uh, in different ways, creating also, uh,
3D configurations.
So at the same time when the kit, you are able
to produce colored pieces, shoulder pieces,
and different kinds of hus.
And last thing about materials.
So of course, um, there are many materials that are suitable
for the laser cut, but it's also true that are materials
that can contain PBC that should be banned.
So anything containing PVC that is poly chloride, uh,
can be toxic because it'll release chlorine
gas when laser are cut.
This is not, uh, harmful for the machine itself,
but also for your health and for the environment.
So always be sure, um, to detect the kind
of material you have at your hand
and try to work with a thickness, uh,
between one or two millimeters.
Uh, synthetic felt wood felt.
Um, it's definitely good to be used for prototyping,
scuba diving, fabric, print fiber, uh, velvet
and also vegetable d, genuine leather when it comes
to cotton linein dan name.
This materials can definitely be laser cut,
but they, they will tear bit.
They're not very good
and suitable for creating interlocking systems.
You can also make use of, um,
you've been talking about sustainability upcycling,
so you can also start collecting fabric waste
and scraps you have at your location.
Always be sure of the kind of material that you have,
uh, before laser cutting.
The full garment, uh, biomaterials of course,
um, can also be used.
And what cannot be used is vinyl
materials containing PBC.
So foam polyester fabric
and also fabrics that are made of mesh.
And the ones that are made in woven, it doesn't really work,
uh, for making interlocking systems.
Uh, I'll not play the video, um, because we're late,
but you cannot always, uh, do what we call a burn test
in order to detect
and understand the kind of material you have at your hand.
Um, there are many tutorials, there are many tables
that compare different materials
or you can just do a simple trick burning a little bit
of the edge of a material with a lighter
and look at the color of the flame that you have.
If it's green in most of the cases it'll contain B, B, C.
So something that you cannot lose a cut at all.
And in short, to summarize, so this is
what your assignment would be.
So your be asked to design prototype also with paper
and scissors, your modular configurations, your modules,
your garment, or whatever you want in
mind that you want to make.
Uh, you'll be asked to document, of course the workflow, um,
the parameter, the tests on the different fabric
and the laser cutting modules, but also the nesting
before assembling.
So it'll be asked also to upload your creation
in this distributed platform, open source,
so secure fashion.com
and provide your best features together with a short, um,
filing PDF, where you can have guidelines
and prescribe everybody on how to best assemble the pieces.
And I think, uh, you can get inspired by what's been there
by all these, uh, creators for academies that shared, uh,
with us for more than nine years.
Uh, um, the creation, there is a lot of other projects
that we can, uh, discuss about.
And, uh, you can find all the documentation linked, um,
on this great platform.
So I really am looking forward
to seeing your creations in a week.
And, uh, thank you.
You also find application linked, uh, the class archive
as well as the, uh, guidelines
that recap, uh, the assignment.
And if, uh, there is questions you can also, um,
unmute yourself or write in the chat.
I was not looking at it.
Yeah, so the material is the most important thing.
Please, uh, double check
fabric waste.
It depends where you, you can bring it to the lab tomorrow.
We can have a look together.
Uh, tomorrow we will be meeting together again at 3:00 PM
CT for our tutorial.
So it can also, um, start downloading a software.
I will put it again on mamos.
We're gonna do something in between Fusion 360 and,
and Rhino for creating a model.
And we'll be also using, um,
Inscape Illustrator, uh, for nesting.
So you have, um, an option at least one
of those four software.
So we'll put, be putting the links there,
we can download the software.
And uh, yeah, if you don't have any questions,
I'm very sorry because I know it's a bit late.
So get inspired, look at the others,
what has been there, look at your wardrobe
and see you next week with the review on open source,
secure fashion.